mayoclinichealthsystem.org 2016-10-11

# Notice of Privacy Practices

Notice of Privacy Practices
Mayo Clinic has always been a leader in protecting patients’ medical information.
Maintaining patient privacy is part of our mission to serve the needs of the patient
first. Controlled use of medical information by staff at Mayo Clinic is essential to
providing optimum patient care.
The United States government created rules for the use and protection of medical
and health information by hospitals, clinics and other medical practices. The
rules are a result of the 1996 Health Insurance Portability and Accountability
Act (HIPAA). They are meant to provide all patients in the United States with
standard privacy protections. One rule requires hospitals and clinics to provide
all patients with a Notice of Privacy Practices to explain how patient medical
information is used. The same rule requires hospitals and clinics to keep records
showing that patients have received the notice.
We are happy to provide you with this copy of Mayo Clinic’s Notice of Privacy
Practices. We hope it will answer any questions you may have about how patient
medical information is used here. In accordance with the federal government
HIPAA rules, please sign the form that came with this notice and bring it with
you to your appointment. Signing the form will show that you have received the
notice; it will in no way affect the care you receive at Mayo Clinic.
If you have questions about anything contained in this notice, please feel free
to contact the site privacy officer for the applicable Mayo Clinic entity. Contact
information for these individuals is provided in the final section of this notice.
Thank you for placing your care, and your trust, in Mayo Clinic.
Sincerely,
John H. Noseworthy, M.D.
President and CEO, Mayo Clinic

THIS NOTICE DESCRIBES HOW MEDICAL INFORMATION ABOUT YOU                         Mayo Clinic’s duties
MAY BE USED AND DISCLOSED AND HOW YOU CAN GET ACCESS                            By law, Mayo Clinic must keep protected health information private.
TO THIS INFORMATION. PLEASE REVIEW IT CAREFULLY.                                The federal government defines protected health information as any
                                                                                information, whether oral, electronic or paper, which is created or
Where this applies                                                              received by Mayo Clinic and relates to a patient’s physical or mental
Mayo Clinic participates in an Organized Health Care Arrangement                health or condition, or payment for the provision of medical services.
(OHCA) under the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act.           This includes not only the results of tests and notes written by doctors,
An OHCA is an arrangement that allows Mayo Clinic entities to share             nurses and other clinical personnel, but also certain demographic
protected health information about their patients or plan members to            information (such as your name, address and telephone number) that is
promote the joint operations of the participating entities. The entities        related to your health records.
covered by this notice, which are listed below in this section, have
formed an OHCA and share PHI with each other. These entities also               Mayo Clinic is required by law to give you this notice and to follow the
have a separate OHCA and share PHI with the Mayo Medical Plan, a                terms and conditions of the notice that is currently in effect. Mayo Clinic
HIPAA Covered Entity that provides medical benefits to Mayo Clinic              will report breaches of your unsecured protected health information as
employees, retirees and their families. Mayo Clinic Health System -             required by law.
Franciscan Medical Center, Inc., Mayo Clinic Health System, Eau Claire
Clinic, Inc., Mayo Clinic Health System- Eau Claire, Hospital Inc., Mayo        How Mayo Clinic fulfills these duties
Clinic Health System - Northland, Inc., Mayo Clinic Health System -             • Mayo Clinic considers patient privacy as part of its mission to serve the
Chippewa Valley, Inc., Mayo Clinic Health System - Oakridge, Inc.,                 needs of the patient first.
and Mayo Clinic Health System – Red Cedar, Inc, also have a separate            • Mayo Clinic takes necessary precautions against inappropriate use or
OHCA and share PHI with Health Tradition Health Plan, a HIPAA                      disclosure of protected health information.
Covered Entity and Mayo owned Wisconsin insurance company that                  • Mayo Clinic employees are expected to access protected health
offers insured medical plans to employers and individuals in the State             information only as necessary to perform their jobs.
of Wisconsin. The Mayo Medical Plan and Health Tradition Health Plan            • Mayo Clinic employees who violate these rules and policies are subject
do not share PHI with each other and are covered by their own separate             to sanctions, including discipline and termination.
Notice of Privacy Practices, which can be found here:
                                                                                The Health Care Providers Covered By This Notice
Health Tradition Health Plan: https://www.healthtradition.com/                  This notice covers Mayo Clinic and Mayo Clinic personnel, volunteers,
members/about/privacy                                                           students, and trainees. The notice also covers other health care
                                                                                providers that come to Mayo Clinic’s facilities to care for patients (such
Mayo Medical Plan: http://www.mayo.edu/pmts/mc0900-mc0999/                      as physicians, physician assistants, therapists, and other health care
mc0937-59.pdf                                                                   providers not employed by Mayo Clinic), unless these other health care
                                                                                providers give you their own notice of privacy practices that describes
This notice applies to the following Mayo Clinic entities and health care       how they will protect your protected health information. Mayo Clinic
practices sites, (collectively referred to as “Mayo Clinic”):                   may share your protected health information with other health care
                                                                                providers for their treatment, payment and health care operations.
Minnesota: Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Mayo Clinic Hospital — Rochester,          This arrangement is only for sharing information and not for any other
Mayo Psychiatry and Psychology Treatment Center (Generose), Mayo                purpose.
Foundation for Medical Education and Research, Mayo Clinic Hospice,
Charter House, Mayo Clinic Pharmacy, Mayo Clinic Store, Mayo                    A Word about Federal and State Law
Medical Laboratories (MML), Mayo Clinic Sports Medicine Centers,                Federal and state laws require Mayo Clinic to protect your medical
Gold Cross Ambulance Service and Mayo Clinic Medical Transport (in              information and federal law requires Mayo Clinic to describe to you how
Minnesota and Wisconsin), Mayo Clinic Express Care locations, the               we handle that information. When federal and state privacy laws differ,
Mayo Family Clinics in Kasson, Kenyon,Northwest Rochester, Northeast            and the state law is more protective of your information or provides
Rochester, and Southeast Rochester. Mayo Clinic Health System sites             you with greater access to your information, then state law will override
in Minnesota, which include operating locations in Adams, Albert Lea,           federal law. For example, where we have specifically identified additional
Alden, Austin, Belle Plaine, Blooming Prarie, Blue Earth, Caledonia,            applicable state law requirements in this notice, the referenced Mayo
Cannon Falls, Elko New Market, Fairmont, Faribault, Farmington,                 entities will follow the more stringent state law requirements.
Janesville, Kenyon, Kiester, La Crescent, Lake City, Lake Crystal,
Lakeville, Lamberton, Le Seur, LeRoy, Lonsdale, Mabel, Mankato,
                                                                                Part I - Most Common Uses and Disclosures
Montgomery, New Prague, New Richland, Northfield, Owatonna,
Plainview, Red Wing, Sherburn, Springfield, St. James, St. Peter, Trimont,      This section describes the most common circumstances in which Mayo
Truman, Wabasha, Waseca, Waterville, Wells, Zumbrota. (collectively             Clinic may use or disclose protected health information.
referred to as “Mayo Clinic in Minnesota Entities”)
                                                                                Treatment
Florida: Mayo Clinic in Jacksonville and its health care practice sites,        Mayo Clinic will use and disclose protected health information to
which include its affiliated hospital and its offsite primary care practices.   provide, coordinate or manage your care. This includes communication
(collectively referred to as “Mayo Clinic in Florida Entities”)                 and consultation between health care providers - doctors, nurses,
                                                                                technicians and other members of your medical team. This applies to
Arizona: Mayo Clinic in Arizona and its health care practice sites , which      disclosures for treatment purposes to health care providers both within
includeits hospital, outpatient clinics and off- site primary care practices    and outside of Mayo Clinic. For example, following orthopedic surgery,
(collectively referred to as “Mayo Clinic in Arizona”).                         your doctor may refer you for rehabilitation. Information will be shared
                                                                                between caregivers to ensure continuity of care.
Iowa: Mayo Clinic Health System sites in Iowa, which include operating
locations in: Armstrong, Decorah, Lake Mills, Waukon (collectively              Additional Applicable State Law Requirements
referred to as “Mayo Clinic in Iowa Entities”)                                  Minnesota Law generally requires patient consent for disclosures of
                                                                                protected health information by Mayo Clinic in Minnesota entities for
Wisconsin: Mayo Clinic Health System which has operating locations              treatment purposes, unless the disclosure is to a Mayo-related entity or
in Alma, Arcadia, Barron, Bloomer, Cameron, Chetek, Charles City,               consent is not possible due to a medical emergency.
Chippewa Falls, Colfax, Eau Claire, Ellsworth, Elmwood, Glenwood City,
Holmen, La Crosse, Menomonie, Mondovi, Onalaska, Osseo, Prairie                 Payment
du Chien, Prairie Farm, Rice Lake, Sparta, Tomah. Health Ventures,              Mayo Clinic will use and disclose protected health information to create
Inc., d/b/a Midelfort Pharmacy & Home Medical, Northwest Wisconsin              bills and collect payment from insurance companies, Medicare and
HomeCare, Inc., Northwest Wisconsin Supportive HomeCare, Inc., WI               other payers. This may include providing information such as dates of
(collectively referred to as Mayo Clinic in Wisconsin Entities”)                service, symptoms, and diagnosis to your insurance company to show
                                                                                that Mayo Clinic provided medical services to you. Mayo Clinic also may
Georgia: The Mayo Clinic in Jacksonville site in Georgia, which has an          disclose protected health information to another health care provider if
operating location in Waycross (collectively referred to as “Mayo Clinic in     such information is needed by the other health care provider to obtain
Georgia Entities”).                                                             payment for medical services provided to you.
                                                                              1

Additional Applicable State Law Requirements                                      our facilities. This information is maintained for Mayo Clinic personnel to
Minnesota law generally requires patient consent for disclosures of               assist family members and other visitors or persons in locating you
protected health information by Mayo Clinic in Minnesota entities for             while you are in Mayo Clinic’s facilities. For example, a relative may wish
payment purposes, unless the disclosure is to a Mayo-related entity.              to visit you in the hospital and would need to know your hospital room
Florida Law generally requires patient consent for disclosures of                 number. A family member meeting you for an appointment may have
protected health information by Mayo Clinic in Florida entities for               forgotten which floor your appointment is on. This information is only
payment purposes..                                                                shared with people who ask for you by name or with members of the
Wisconsin law generally requires patient consent to disclose HIV test             clergy. If you indicate a religious affiliation, it will be shared only with
results for payment purposes.                                                     members of the clergy. You can choose not to have such information
                                                                                  released from the facility directory/patient census. If you do not want
Health care operations                                                            Mayo Clinic to release such information, please inform the person
Mayo Clinic will use and disclose protected health information if it is           assisting you during registration and/or admission.
necessary to improve the quality of care we provide to patients or to run
                                                                                  Additional Applicable State Law Requirements
our health care facilities. These include activities to monitor and improve
                                                                                  Wisconsin law requires patient consent for disclosure of your health
patient care, license staff to care for patients, prepare for state and federal
                                                                                  condition. Mayo Clinic in Wisconsin entities will not identify you in
regulatory reviews, train health care and non health care professionals,
                                                                                  the Facility Directory as receiving, or having received, mental health
manage health care operations, and improve health care services. Here
                                                                                  treatment without patient consent, and generally requires patient consent
are some examples:
                                                                                  to disclose such information, except as required or authorized by law.
• To reduce the infection rate after a surgery, it would be necessary
   to look at medical records to determine the rate of infections that
                                                                                  Family Members and Others Involved in Your Care
   occurred.
                                                                                  Mayo Clinic may disclose relevant protected health information to a
• To be licensed to do a certain procedure, a doctor may be required
                                                                                  family member or friend who is involved with your care. We find that
   to show that he or she has successfully completed a number of
                                                                                  many patients want us to discuss their care with their family members
   procedures under the supervision of another physician.
                                                                                  and others to keep them up-to-date on your care, to help you understand
• A Federal Drug Administration inspector may review patient records
                                                                                  your care, to help in handling your bills, or to help in the scheduling of
   in a laboratory to ensure that accurate and complete records are
                                                                                  your appointments. In a disaster situation, we also may disclose relevant
   maintained for patient safety.
                                                                                  protected health information to disaster relief organizations to help
                                                                                  locate your family members or friends or to inform them of your location,
Mayo facilities across the country, including but not limited to Mayo
                                                                                  condition or death. If family members or friends are present while care is
Clinic in Rochester, Mayo Clinic in Florida and Mayo Clinic in Arizona,
                                                                                  being provided, Mayo Clinic will assume your companions may hear the
and the Mayo Clinic Health System clinics and hospitals in Georgia,
                                                                                  discussion, unless you state otherwise. If you do not want Mayo Clinic
Iowa, Minnesota and Wisconsin, also work closely together to improve
                                                                                  to disclose your protected health information to your family members
health care operations across the Mayo Clinic system, and we may use
                                                                                  or others who are involved with your care or handling your bills, please
protected health information for those activities.
                                                                                  inform the person assisting you during registration and/or admission.
                                                                                  Mayo Clinic may also disclose your protected health information to a
Mayo Clinic may also disclose protected health information to another
                                                                                  personal representative who has authority to make health care decisions
health care provider who has treated you, or to your insurance company,
                                                                                  on your behalf.
if such information is needed for certain health care operations of the
health care provider or insurance company, such as quality improvement            Additional Applicable State Law Requirements
activities, evaluations of health care professionals, and state and federal       Wisconsin law generally requires patient consent to share protected
regulatory reviews.                                                               health information with family members or friends, except as required or
                                                                                  authorized by law.
Additional Applicable State Law Requirements
Minnesota law generally requires patient consent for disclosures of
                                                                                  Medical Research
protected health information by Mayo Clinic in Minnesota Entities for
                                                                                  Medical research is vital to the advancement of medical science. Federal
health care operations purposes, unless the disclosure is to a Mayo-
                                                                                  regulations permit use of protected health information in medical
related entity.
                                                                                  research, either with your authorization, when your name and most other
Florida law generally requires patient consent for disclosures of
                                                                                  identifiers have been removed and the recipient of the information signs
protected health information by Mayo Clinic in Florida Entities for health
                                                                                  a data use agreement, or when the research study at Mayo Clinic
care operations purposes.
                                                                                  is reviewed and approved by an Institutional Review Board before any
Wisconsin law generally requires patient consent to disclose HIV test
                                                                                  medical research study begins. In some situations, limited information
results for certain health care operations.
                                                                                  may be used before approval of the research study to allow a researcher
                                                                                  to determine whether enough patients exist to make a study scientifically
Patient contacts
                                                                                  valid.
At times, Mayo Clinic may access information, such as your name,
address and general medical condition to contact you to:                          Additional Applicable State Law Requirements
• set up or remind you about future appointments; provide information             Minnesota law generally requires patient consent for disclosures of
   about treatment alternatives or other information that may be of               protected health information by Mayo Clinic in Minnesota Entities
   interest to you; or                                                            to outside researchers for medical research purposes. Mayo Clinic in
• disclose health-related benefits or services that may be of interest to         Minnesota Entities will obtain such consent from their patients or
   you.                                                                           refusal to participate in any research study, or will make a good faith
                                                                                  effort to obtain such consent or refusal, before releasing any identifiable
Additional Applicable State Law Requirements
                                                                                  information to an outside researcher for research purposes.
Florida law generally requires patient consent for Mayo Clinic in Florida
                                                                                  Wisconsin law generally requires patient consent before we may
entities to contact their patients for purposes of providing information
                                                                                  disclose protected health information for research purposes to a
regarding treatment alternatives, services, or goods.
                                                                                  researcher who is not affiliated with Mayo Clinic. In some situations,
                                                                                  Mayo Clinic may disclose protected health information for research
Philanthropy
                                                                                  purposes to a researcher who agrees to protect the privacy of your
Mayo Clinic may contact you to raise funds to sustain the Mayo mission,
                                                                                  information. Private pay patients may be able to opt out of the use or
but you may contact us and request not to receive any future fundraising
                                                                                  disclosure of your information for research purposes.
communications. Mayo Clinic does not sell or rent patients’ names or
                                                                                  Florida law generally requires patient consent for disclosures of
addresses to any organization outside of Mayo.
                                                                                  identifiable health information by Mayo Clinic in Florida entities to
                                                                                  outside researchers for medical research purposes.
Facility Directory/Patient Census
                                                                                  Georgia law generally requires patient consent for disclosures of
Mayo Clinic may include your name, location in a facility, health
                                                                                  protected health information to outside researchers for medical research
condition (in general terms, such as “good,” “fair”) and religious
                                                                                  purposes.
affiliation (should you choose to provide one) in current patient lists for
                                                                                2

Part II Other Potential Uses and Disclosures                                     Law Enforcement Activities
                                                                                 Mayo Clinic may disclose protected health information to law
This section describes the less common circumstances in which Mayo               enforcement officials. For example, we may release protected health
Clinic may use or disclose protected health information.                         information to law enforcement officials:
                                                                                 • in response to a valid court order, grand jury subpoena, or search warrant;
To Avert a Serious Threat of Harm                                                • to identify a suspect, fugitive or missing person;
Mayo Clinic may use and disclose protected health information to alert           • about the victim of a crime under certain limited circumstances;
those able to prevent or lessen a serious and immediate threat to the            • about a death believed to be a result of criminal conduct; or
health or safety of a patient, another person or the public.                     • about a crime committed on Mayo Clinic premises.
Organ and Tissue Donation                                                        Additional Applicable State Law Requirements
If Mayo Clinic professionals determine that a patient might be a                 Minnesota law generally requires patient consent for disclosures of
candidate for organ or tissue donation, Mayo Clinic may release                  protected health information by Mayo Clinic in Minnesota Entities for
protected health information to organizations that handle organ                  law enforcement purposes, unless the disclosure is in response to a valid
procurement, or organ, eye, tissue donation banks, or other health               court order or warrant.
care organizations as needed to make organ or tissue donation and                Iowa law does not allow the disclosure of information regarding
transplantation possible.                                                        substance abuse to any law enforcement officer or law enforcement
Additional Applicable State Law Requirements                                     agency unless you have authorized the disclosure. (see by law below
Wisconsin law generally requires patient consent to disclose mental              which addresses this)
health treatment records for organ or tissue donation purposes.                  Wisconsin law generally requires patient consent for disclosures of
                                                                                 protected health information for law enforcement purposes, unless the
Military Personnel                                                               disclosure is otherwise authorized or required by law.
If a patient is a member of the United States Armed Forces, Mayo
Clinic may release protected health information as required by military          Coroners, Medical Examiners and Funeral Directors
authorities. Mayo Clinic also may release protected health information           Mayo Clinic may release protected health information to a coroner or
about foreign military personnel to the appropriate foreign military             medical examiner when necessary to identify the deceased, determine the
authority. When the military organization is sponsoring the medical              cause of death or as otherwise authorized by law. Mayo Clinic also may
evaluation, the patient’s protected health information is shared with both       release protected health information to a funeral director as necessary
the patient and the sponsoring organization. Patients being evaluated on         to carry out the funeral director’s duties, including arrangements after
behalf of the military should be aware of these arrangements.                    death.
Additional Applicable State Law Requirements                                     Additional Applicable State Law Requirements
Minnesota law generally requires patient consent for disclosures of              Minnesota law generally requires the consent of a patient’s authorized
protected health information by Mayo Clinic in Minnesota Entities for the        family or legal representative for disclosures of protected health
military purposes referenced above, unless the disclosure is specifically        information by Mayo Clinic in Minnesota entities to funeral directors.
required by federal law.                                                         Wisconsin law generally requires consent of a patient’s authorized
Wisconsin law generally requires patient consent to disclose information         family or legal representative to release protected health information to
from your mental health treatment records or HIV test results, unless the        funeral directors, however, HIV test results and certain other protected
disclosure is otherwise authorized or required by law.                           health information may be disclosed to a funeral director when necessary
                                                                                 to permit the funeral director to carry out his/ her duties. Wisconsin
Workers’ Compensation                                                            law generally requires consent of a patient’s authorized family or legal
Mayo Clinic may disclose protected health information for workers’               representative or a court order to release mental health treatment records
compensation or similar programs as authorized or required by law.               to a coroner or medical examiner.
These programs provide benefits for work-related injuries or illness.            National Security Activities
                                                                                 Mayo Clinic may release protected health information to authorized
Public Health Purposes                                                           federal officials for intelligence, counterintelligence or other national
Mayo Clinic may disclose protected health information for public health          security activities authorized by law. Mayo Clinic also may disclose
purposes. The following are some examples of releases that are allowed           protected health information to authorized federal officials so they may
for public health purposes:                                                      provide protection to the President or other authorized individuals.
• to report vital statistics (e.g., births, deaths);
• to report to the federal government adverse reactions to medication or         Additional Applicable State Law Requirements
   safety problems with FDA-regulated products;                                  Minnesota law generally requires patient consent for disclosures of
• to notify people of product recalls; and to report communicable                protected health information by Mayo Clinic in Minnesota entities for
   diseases to local, county, state, and federal health officials.               national security purposes, unless the disclosure is specifically required by
                                                                                 federal law.
Additional Applicable State Law Requirements                                     Florida law generally requires patient consent for disclosures of
Wisconsin law generally requires patient consent to disclose information         protected health information by Mayo Clinic in Florida entities for
from your mental health treatment records and your HIV test results,             national security purposes, unless the disclosure is specifically required by
unless the disclosure is otherwise authorized or required by law.                federal law.
                                                                                 Wisconsin law generally requires patient consent for disclosures of
Health Oversight Activities                                                      protected health information for national security purposes, unless the
Mayo Clinic may disclose protected health information to health                  disclosure is specifically required by federal law.
oversight agencies that oversee our operations or personnel. For example
Mayo Clinic may need to disclose protected health information to the             Required by Law
state agencies that oversee our health care facilities or licensed health care   Mayo Clinic will use or disclose protected health information when
personnel (e.g., Department of Health, Medical Board, Nursing Board),            required by federal, state, or local laws. For example, Mayo Clinic is
or the federal agencies that oversee Medicare. These agencies need such          required to report certain gunshot wounds and other injuries that may
information to monitor our compliance with state and federal laws.               have resulted from an unlawful act, and abuse or neglect of a child or
                                                                                 vulnerable adult.
Lawsuits and Other Judicial Proceedings                                          Permitted by Law
Mayo Clinic may disclose protected health information in response to             Mayo Clinic may use or disclose protected health information when
a valid court or administrative order. Mayo Clinic also may disclose             permitted by federal, state, or local laws. For example, some Mayo
protected health information in response to certain types of subpoenas,          Clinic entities are permitted to make a report to the Department of
discovery requests or other lawful process.                                      Transportation regarding a patient’s ability to drive when the report is
                                                                                 necessary to prevent or lessen a threat to the health or safety of a person
                                                                                 or the public.
                                                                               3

                                                                              • the request is not in writing or does not include a supporting reason;
Uses and Disclosures Pursuant to an Authorization                             • the information you want to change was not created by Mayo
Except as described in this notice or specifically required or permitted         Clinic, and the originator of the information is available to make the
by law, Mayo Clinic will not use or disclose your protected health               amendment;
information without your specific written authorization. At times, a Mayo     • the information is not part of the designated medical record; or
Clinic entity may ask you to provide specific written permission to allow     • the information in the record is accurate and complete.
the Mayo Clinic entity to use or disclose protected health information
about you. Mayo Clinic generally will not use or disclose your protected      If Mayo Clinic denies your request for an amendment, Mayo Clinic will
health information for marketing purposes, in exchange for remuneration,      give you a written explanation of the denial. If you still disagree with
or use or disclose any psychotherapy notes about you unless Mayo              the explanation provided, you can submit your written disagreement to
Clinic receives your authorization to do so. A valid authorization may        Mayo Clinic as referenced above, or you can ask that your request for
be revoked in writing at any time. Written revocation of authorization        amendment and explanation of the denial, or an accurate summary of
must be submitted to the applicable Mayo Clinic entity and addressed to       such information, be included in any future disclosure of the pertinent
the Health Information Management Services. Once the authorization            protected health information. If you submit a statement of disagreement,
is revoked, the Mayo Clinic entity will no longer be allowed to use or        Mayo Clinic may include a rebuttal statement addressing your statement
disclose protected health information for the purposes described in the       of disagreement in the designated medical record.
authorization except to the extent the Mayo Clinic entity has already
taken action based upon the authorization.                                    Right to a List of Certain Disclosures
                                                                              You can ask Mayo Clinic for a list of the persons or organizations to
Information with Additional Protections                                       which Mayo Clinic has disclosed your protected health information. This
Certain types of protected health information may have additional             list would provide you with a summary of certain disclosures Mayo Clinic
protection under federal or state law. For example, protected health          has made that you would not otherwise be in a position to know about.
information about mental health, HIV/AIDS and genetic testing results         The following are examples of disclosures that would not be included in
is treated differently than other types of protected health information       the list:
under certain state laws. Additionally, federally assisted alcohol and drug   • disclosures to carry out treatment, payment and health care operations;
abuse programs are subject to certain special restrictions on the use and     • disclosures made directly to you (the patient) or disclosures that you
disclosure of alcohol and drug abuse treatment information. To the extent        have specifically authorized;
applicable, Mayo Clinic would need to get your written permission before      • disclosures made from the facility directory/patient census;
disclosing that information to others in many circumstances.                  • disclosures to persons involved in your care;
                                                                              • disclosures incident to a use or disclosure that is otherwise permitted or
                                                                                 required by law;
Part III Patients’ Rights with Respect to Protected                           • disclosures made for national security or intelligence purposes;
Health Information                                                            • disclosures made to correctional institutions or law enforcement
                                                                                 officials having custody over a patient; or
This section describes the rights of Mayo Clinic patients to protected        • disclosures that took place before April 14, 2003.
health information.
                                                                              To obtain a copy of the list, submit a written request to the applicable
Right to Inspect and Copy                                                     Mayo Clinic entity and address the request to the attention of the
You have the right to inspect and to request a copy of information            Site Privacy Officer. Your request must state a time period (beginning
maintained in Mayo Clinic’s designated medical record about you. This         no earlier than April 14, 2003 when the federal privacy rules go into
includes medical and billing records maintained and used by Mayo Clinic       effect and for no longer than six years). The first list requested within
to make decisions about your care.                                            a 12-month period shall be provided at no charge. For additional lists
                                                                              requested during the same 12-month period, Mayo Clinic may charge for
To obtain or inspect a copy of your protected health information, submit      the costs of providing the list.
a written request to the applicable Mayo Clinic entity and address the
request to the attention of the Health Information Management Services.       Right to Request Restrictions
Mayo Clinic generally may charge a reasonable, cost-based fee to cover        You can ask Mayo Clinic to restrict the use or disclosure of protected
the expense of providing copies. Mayo Arizona Entities are not permitted      health information about you for treatment, payment, or health care
under Arizona law to charge a fee if the information is needed for            operations. Your request must be in writing and submitted to the
treatment purposes.                                                           applicable Mayo Clinic entity. The request should also be addressed
                                                                              to the attention of the Site Privacy Officer. Mayo Clinic will carefully
Most patients have full access to inspect and receive a copy of the full      consider all requests. However, because of the integrated nature of
medical record. On rare occasions, Mayo Clinic may deny a request to          Mayo Clinic’s medical record, Mayo Clinic is not generally able to honor
inspect and receive a copy of some information in the medical record.         most requests, nor is Mayo Clinic legally required to do so. If you or
For example, this may occur if, in the professional judgment of a patient’s   someone on your behalf pays for a health care item or service in full,
physician, the release of the information would be reasonably likely to       you can request that Mayo Clinic not disclose information about the
endanger the life or physical safety of the patient or another person.        item or service to your health plan for payment or health care operations
                                                                              purposes, and Mayo Clinic will agree to your request unless required by
Right to Request Alternate Methods of Communication                           law to make the disclosure.
You have a right to request that Mayo Clinic communicate with you in
certain ways (such as a letter or by phone) or at a certain location. For     Right to Notice of Privacy Practices
example, you may ask that we contact you only at home or only at your         You have the right to obtain a paper copy of this notice upon request,
place of business. In this situation, you may submit a written request to     even if you have agreed to receive the notice electronically. To obtain
the applicable Mayo Clinic entity specifying the communication method         a paper copy of this notice, submit a written request to the any Mayo
or alternative location being requested. The request should be addressed      Clinic entity. The request should be addressed to the attention of the Site
to the attention of the Site Privacy Officer. Mayo Clinic will accommodate    Privacy Officer.
reasonable requests. However, if the request could result in Mayo Clinic
not being able to collect for services or cause significant administrative
burden, Mayo Clinic reserves the right to require you to provide
additional information about how payment for services will be handled.
Right to Request Amendment
You have the right to request that your protected health information in
Mayo Clinic’s designated medical record for you be amended. If you wish
to request amendment of the information in your record, submit a written
request to the applicable Mayo Clinic entity and address the request
to the attention of the Health Information Management Services. The
request must include a reason to support the amendment.
Mayo Clinic may deny a request for amendment based upon any of the
following circumstances:
                                                                            4

Complaints                                                                        Need More Information?
If you want to file a complaint or express concerns about Mayo Clinic’s           If you have any questions, or would like to discuss this notice in more
use or disclosure of Protected Health Information, please contact the             detail, please contact the privacy officer for the applicable Mayo Clinic
applicable Mayo Clinic entity as follows:                                         entity.
Mayo Clinic in Minnesota, Iowa, and Wisconsin Entities:                           • Mayo Clinic in Minnesota Entities:
   Mayo Clinic in Rochester                                                       		         Privacy Officer – 507-266-6286
   Attn: Office of Patient Experience                                             		         http://www.mayoclinic.org/
   200 First Street S.W.                                                          • Mayo Clinic in Florida Entities:
   Rochester, Minnesota 55905                                                     		         Privacy Officer – 904-953-2930
   Phone: 507-284-4988                                                            		         http://www.mayoclinic.org/jacksonville/
Mayo Clinic in Florida and Georgia Entities:                                      • Mayo Clinic in Arizona Entities:
   Mayo Clinic in Jacksonville                                                    		         Privacy Officer – 480-342-2287
   Attn: Privacy Officer                                                          		         http://www.mayoclinic.org/scottsdale/
   4500 San Pablo Road                                                            • Mayo Clinic Health System Entities:
   Jacksonville, Florida 32224                                                    		         http://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/
   Phone: 904-953-2930                                                            		         Privacy Officers by location:
Mayo Clinic in Arizona Entities:                                                     Southeast Minnesota Region – 507-377-6272
   Mayo Clinic in Arizona                                                         		         Includes Albert Lea, Alden, Farmington, Kiester, MN, Lake
   Attn: Patient Administrative Liaison Office                                               Includes Albert Lea, Alden, Farmington, Kiester, MN, Lake
   13400 East Shea Boulevard                                                                 Mills, Charles City, IA, New Richland, Wells, Austin, Adams,
   Scottsdale, Arizona 85259                                                                 LeRoy, Cannon Falls, Lakeville, Faribault, MN, Red Wing,
   Phone: 480-301-4938                                                                       Zumbrota, Kenyon, Blooming Prairie, MN, Ellsworth, WI,
                                                                                             Wabasha, Elko New Market, Northfield, Owatonna, Lake City,
You also may file a written complaint with the United States Department                      Plainview, Lonsdale, MN, Alma, WI
of Health and Human Services – Office for Civil Rights. Mayo Clinic                  Southwest Minnesota Region – 507-385-2646
honors your right to express concerns regarding your privacy. Mayo                		         Includes Armstrong, IA, Fairmont, Blue Earth, Sherburn,
Clinic would not – nor could it legally or ethically – take action against
                                                                                             Montgomery, Truman, Waseca, Mankato, Janesville, Lake
you for filing a concern or complaint regarding the use, disclosure, and
                                                                                             Crystal, Lamberton, Belle Plaine, New Prague, Springfield,
rights of your protected health information.
                                                                                             St. James, St. Peter, Trimont, Waterville, Le Sueur, MN
Key Information about this Notice                                                    Northwest Wisconsin Region – 715-838-3646
• This is a revised notice for the Mayo entities and health care practice         		         Includes Eau Claire, Chippewa Falls, Osseo, Mondovi, Barron,
   sites referenced on the first page (collectively referred to as “Mayo                     Cameron, Chetek, Prairie Farm, Bloomer, Colfax, Rice Lake,
   Clinic”). The effective date of this revised notice is December 1, 2015.                  Menomonie, Elmwood, Glenwood City, WI, Northwest Health
• From time to time, Mayo Clinic may change its practices concerning                         Ventures, Inc., d/b/a Midelfort Pharmacy & Home Medical,
   how we use or disclose protected health information, or how we will                       Northwest Wisconsin HomeCare, Inc., Northwest Wisconsin
   implement patient rights concerning their information. Mayo Clinic                        Supportive HomeCare, Inc., WI
   reserves the right to change the terms of this notice and make the
   new notice provisions effective for all protected health information              Southwest Wisconsin Region – 608-392-3968
   maintained by Mayo Clinic. Mayo Clinic will follow the terms and               		         Includes La Crosse, Onalaska, WI, Arcadia, WI, Caledonia, MN,
   conditions of the notice that is currently in effect.                                     Decorah, IA, Holmen, WI, La Crescent, Mabel, MN, Sparta, WI,
• When the notice is revised, it will be posted at Mayo Clinic facilities.                   Tomah, WI, Waukon, IA, Prairie du Chien, WI
   It will also be available upon request at Mayo Clinic facilities, by mail,        Georgia – 904-953-2930
   and on the Mayo Clinic’s website at http://www.mayoclinic.org/.                		         Includes Waycross, GA
Applies to Mayo Clinic locations in Arizona, Florida, Rochester and Mayo Clinic Health System.
©2015 Mayo Foundation for Medical Education and Research                                                                                       MC5256-01rev1115
